Guide to the Dorothy Floerchinger Papers 1883-1991
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Dorothy Floerchinger Papers
1883-1991
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 342
Floerchinger, Dorothy, 1901-1996
32.5 linear feet, including 105 volumes
Dorothy Floerchinger was a Montana resident and amateur historian. This collection contains a manuscript written by Floerchinger, clippings and research materials on the Conrad family of Kalispell, Montana, and scrapbooks reflecting her personal interests into historic events throughout Montana and the rest of the United States.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Floerchinger, the daughter of Ralph and Willie Mae Bracegirdle Bruner, was born on February 22, 1901, in Scotia, Nebraska. Graduating from Valier High School in Great Falls, Montana, in 1920, Mrs. Floerchinger began a career of teaching in Pondera County Schools. Due to an acute teacher shortage following World War I, the State Superintendent of Schools issued a special permit allowing her to teach elementary school with no professional training. She married Louis Floerchinger on November 15, 1924 and raised five children on the family farm near Conrad, Montana.
Throughout her life, Mrs. Floerchinger was an avid historian. Mrs. Floerchinger published several historical pieces on Northern Montana - from the history of the City of Conrad to the history of Pondera County. She did extensive research on the Conrad family of Kalispell, who founded the city of Conrad, and was involved in the preservation of local Conrad history. She also wrote literary pieces, publishing an anthology of poems and short stories called Highway to Happiness, a biographical tribute to a Conrad minister and humanitarian called To Speak of Love Was Not Enough, and her family history, The Bruner Bunch.
Mrs. Floerchinger was active in many organizations, including the Montana Library Association, the Montana Farmer's Union, and the Montana Democratic Party. Besides an interest in history, Mrs. Floerchinger was a poet and an artist. Mrs. Floerchinger died in Choteau, Montana, on May 8, 1996.
This collection contains a manuscript written by Mrs. Floerchinger, clippings and research materials on the Conrad family of Kalispell, Montana, and scrapbooks reflecting Mrs. Floerchinger's personal interests into historic events throughout Montana and the rest of the United States. Particular subjects include the history of the Marias River Valley; the history of Conrad, Montana; the Whoop-Up Trail; and Montana organizations, including the Montana Democratic Party, the Montana Farmers Union, and the Montana Library Association.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Manuscript, 1 folder, 1977
Series II: Conrad Family Research, 3 folders, 1883-1978
Series III: Scrapbooks, 105 volumes, 1940-1991
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
All materials in this collection were collected and retained by Dorothy Floerchinger until donation to the K. Ross Toole Archives.
Gifts of Dorothy Floerchinger, 1973, 1978, 1981, 1985, 1986, 1989, 1990, and 1991
A ledger book from Clinton, Virginia, 1882-1883; an indenture from Cumberland County, Virginia, 1828; and a Confederate flag were removed during processing and de-accessioned.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Women authors, American--Montana; Women historians--Montana
Scrapbooks--Montana
Arts--Montana; Education--Montana; Persian Gulf War, 1991
Conrad (Mont.)--History; Marias River Valley (Mont.)--History; Montana--Centennial celebrations, etc.; Montana--History; Whoop-Up Trail
Russell, Charles M. (Charles Marion), 1864-1926--Correspondence
Conrad family
Democratic Party (Mont.); Montana Farmers Union; Montana Library Association
Montana; Scrapbooks; Women
- Manuscript, 1977; Series I; 1 folder
  This series contains a manuscript written by Mrs. Floerchinger called "Quietly Flows Maria's River." The manuscript is somewhat a history of the Marias River, which is located in northern Montana. Included within the text are various maps of the area and a letter from Charles M. Russell regarding the Marias River and the Whoop-Up Trail, which is also located in northern Montana.
  - Manuscript, "Quietly Flows Maria's River", 1997 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Conrad Family Research, 1883-1978; Series II; 3 folders
  Contained within this series are correspondence, biographical information, and clippings regarding the Conrad family of Kalispell and north central Montana. The correspondence is between Mrs. Floerchinger and several Conrad descendants and generally regards mutual requests for information on the family. Mrs. Floerchinger includes biographical information on the Conrad Family, such as histories written by others and a Conrad family tree. Clippings included in this series relate to various Conrad family events, such as weddings and funerals, along with any other news worthy items involving members of the Conrad family (society columns and business articles).
  - Correspondence and research, Conrad Family, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Clippings, Conrad Family, 1883-1978 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Clippings, Conrad Family, 1883-1978 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Scrapbooks, 1940-1991; Series III; 105 volumes
  This series contains scrapbooks assembled by Mrs. Floerchinger. The first 50 scrapbooks reflect Mrs. Floerchinger's personal life; they include vacation mementos, letters, birthday and other holiday cards, news clippings, and various items relating to her interests (local Conrad events, the Montana Farmer's Union, the Montana Library Association, and the Montana Democratic Party). The remaining scrapbooks deal with various subjects, such as the Persian Gulf War, arts in Montana, education in Montana, and Montana history (in particular the Centennial Celebration in 1989). The majority of the scrapbooks are composed of news clippings regarding each subject.
  The scrapbooks relating to Mrs. Floerchinger's personal life are arranged in chronological order; the remaining scrapbooks are grouped according to subject.
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1940-1952 (Volume 1)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1953 (Volume 2)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1954 (Volume 3)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1955 (Volume 4)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1955 (Volume 5)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1956 (Volume 6)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1956 (Volume 7)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1957 (Volume 8)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1957 (Volume 9)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1958 (Volume 10)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1958 (Volume 11)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1959 (Volume 12)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1959 (Volume 13)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1960 (Volume 14)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1960 (Volume 15)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1961 (Volume 16)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1961 (Volume 17)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1962 (Volume 18)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1962 (Volume 19)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1963 (Volume 20)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1963 (Volume 21)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1963 (Volume 22)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1964 (Volume 23)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1964 (Volume 24)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1965 (Volume 25)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1965 (Volume 26)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1966 (Volume 27)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1966 (Volume 28)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1967 (Volume 29)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1967 (Volume 30)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1968 (Volume 31)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1968 (Volume 32)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1969 (Volume 33)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1969 (Volume 34)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1970 (Volume 35)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1970 (Volume 36)
  - Montana, 1971-1984 (Volume 37)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1982-1983 (Volume 38)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1983-1984 (Volume 39)
  - Montana, 1980-1983 (Volume 40)
  - Conrad, Montana, 75th Anniversary, 1984 (Volume 41)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1985 (Volume 42)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1985 (Volume 43)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1986 (Volume 44)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1986 (Volume 45)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1987 (Volume 46)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1987 (Volume 47)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1988 (Volume 48)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1988 (Volume 49)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1989 (Volume 50)
  - Dorothy Floerchinger, 1990 (Volume 51)
  - Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Volume 52)
  - Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Volume 53)
  - Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Volume 54)
  - Lewis & Clark (Volume 55)
  - "Toole County, Fort Benton, Highland Journal" (Volume 56)
  - "True Tales of the American Front - Montana" (Volume 57)
  - "True Tales of Montana Authors" (Volume 58)
  - "History" (Volume 59)
  - "History" (Volume 60)
  - Art in Montana/New Interpretations (Volume 61)
  - "Art in Montana" (Volume 62)
  - "Knees MT" (Volume 63)
  - "Pageants by Dorothy Floerchinger" (Volume 64)
  - Montana Centennial, 1889-1989 (Volume 65)
  - Montana Centennial, 1889-1989 (Volume 66)
  - Montana Centennial, 1889-1989 (Volume 67)
  - Montana Centennial, 1889-1989 (Volume 68)
  - "Places" (Volume 69)
  - "Places" (Volume 70)
  - "Places" (Volume 71)
  - "Places" (Volume 72)
  - "Places" (Volume 73)
  - "Visual Arts" (Volume 74)
  - "Visual Arts" (Volume 75)
  - "Visual Arts" (Volume 76)
  - "Visual Arts" (Volume 77)
  - "Performing Arts" (Volume 78)
  - "Performing Arts" (Volume 79)
  - "Performing Arts" (Volume 80)
  - "Performing Arts" (Volume 81)
  - "Paul Dyck" (Volume 82)
  - "People" (Volume 83)
  - "People" (Volume 84)
  - "People" (Volume 85)
  - "People" (Volume 86)
  - "Education" (Volume 87)
  - "Education" (Volume 88)
  - "Education" (Volume 89)
  - "Writers" (Volume 90)
  - "Writers" (Volume 91)
  - "Writers" (Volume 92)
  - "Writing" (Volume 93)
  - "Montana People Doing Things" (Volume 94)
  - "Montana People Doing Things" (Volume 95)
  - "Montana People" (Volume 96)
  - "Montana People and Places" (Volume 97)
  - "Indians" (Volume 98)
  - "Indians" (Volume 99)
  - "Indians" (Volume 100)
  - "Montanans of Note" (Volume 101)
  - "The Piegan Storyteller" (Volume 102)
  - "The Piegan Storyteller" (Volume 103)
  - "The Piegan Storyteller" (Volume 104)
  - Piegan Storyteller notes (Volume 105)